Alright בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is officially צדי ג.
Tzadi Gimmel. We're a little bit behind. We pick up at the
bottom of
צדי ב עמוד א, Tzadi Beis Amud Aleph, the last two words.
We're dealing with a משנה Mishnah that says that speaks about a
woman whose again husband goes far away, but then there are contradictory
testimonies. First testimony that he's dead and specifically around the יבום Yibum
משנה Mishnah that he died first and then and then the sons
died, so she got married and then it turned out that it
was the reverse. So it turned out that she was a woman
who required יבום Yibum or חליצה Chalitzah that married somebody else and
the משנה Mishnah says that the child is a ממזר mamzer and
again not to review what we did yesterday, but it seems pretty
clear the משנה Mishnah is dealing not with all of the negative
rabbinic קנסות knassos but with the דאורייתא d'Oraisa consequences and it says
why is the child a ממזר? mamzer? I mean this is a
woman who needs חליצה Chalitzah but why is the child a ממזר?
mamzer? This is going according to רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva that says
that you get a ממזר mamzer that there would not be קידושין
kiddushin in a case of an איסור לאו, issur lav, a simple
negative prohibition, and that the and relatedly that the child would be
a ממזר mamzer in this case, so this משנה Mishnah is according
to רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. So now the גמרא Gemara continues three
words from the bottom of צדי ב עמוד א. Tzadi Beis Amud
Aleph. אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda said רב יהודה אמר רב
Rav Yehuda amar Rav in the name of רב Rav or רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda I guess it was אמר רב. amar Rav רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda אמר רב amar Rav. מניין minayin top צדי ב
עמוד ב Tzadi Beis Amud Beis מניין שאין קידושין תופסין ביבמה. minayin
she'ein kiddushin tofsin b'yevamah.
How do you know? Forget רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, might be true
that רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva is the only one that says that
the child of חייבי לאוין chayei lavin is a ממזר. mamzer. But
he says, and this is clear from the ראשונים, Rishonim, that there's
really a position when it comes to a יבמה yevamah that everybody
would agree that forget רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva that you could not
marry a woman who was in a state of requiring you know
who was a זקוקה ליבום zekukah l'yibum who was requiring יבום yibum
or חליצה chalitzah and the logic you understand because if going back
to יבום yibum concepts, if this woman has זיקה zikah and you
know the connection to her husband, the marriage to her husband is
somewhat continuing through the brother-in-law until that is fully actualized through יבום
yibum or fully released through חליצה, chalitzah, then it's not just an
איסור לאו, issur lav, it's not the איסור issur that stands away
in her marrying somebody else, it's the fact that she's already quasi-married
to her brother-in-law. So that's what he says, forget רבי עקיבא, Rebbi
Akiva, how do you know everybody should agree that there is no
קידושין kiddushin with this woman who is awaiting יבום yibum or חליצה?
chalitzah? מניין שאין קידושין תופסין ביבמה minayin she'ein kiddushin tofsin b'yevamah שנאמר
shene'emar the verse says לא תהיה אשת המת החוצה לאיש זר, lo
tihiyeh eishesh hames hachutzah l'ish zar, the wife of the dead shall
not be to the outside to a foreign man.
So that should be read as a prohibition, she shall not marry
another man before she gets חליצה, chalitzah, but it could also mean
לא תהיה בהויה לזר lo tihiyeh bahavayah l'zar that it won't be
binding, she cannot be married to a foreign man, it won't even
take effect, okay? And that's what רב Rav says that everybody will
agree it won't take effect. So again, nobody's debating that the משנה
Mishnah that the child is a ממזר mamzer is limited to a
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva position, but the idea that she can't be
married and קידושין kiddushin won't take effect, he says that everybody would
agree to.
The דרשה drasha is on the word
תהיה, tihiyeh, right, it won't even take effect, not just it's not
allowed. ושמואל אמר Ushmuel amar שמואל Shmuel says בעניותינו צריכה גט. ba'aniyoseinu
tzrichah get.
She does require a
גט. get. Okay, now either he's saying that actually קידושין kiddushin חל,
chal, but the גמרא Gemara reads this that he's not sure, presumably
based on the word בעניותינו ba'aniyoseinu in our humility. So the גמרא
Gemara says מספקא ליה לשמואל mesapkala lei l'Shmuel שמואל Shmuel has a
doubt האי לא תהיה אשת המת hai lo tihiyeh eishesh hames when
it says that the woman shall not be to the outside world,
does it mean אילו לאו הוא דאתא ilu lav hu d'asa is
it just saying it's a prohibition but if you do it it
takes effect, אילו לא תפסי בה קידושין הוא דאתא ilo lo tafsi
bei kiddushin hu d'asa or is it saying like רב Rav read
it that it doesn't even take effect? So he says I'm going
to demand that she gets a גט get and the way the
גמרא Gemara interprets that means I'm going to demand at least מספק
misafek she gets a גט, get, maybe the קידושין kiddushin does take
effect. One minute. אמר ליה רב מרי בר רחל לרב אשי Amar
lei Rav Mari bar Rachel l'Rav Ashi so רב מרי בר רחל
Rav Mari bar Rachel said to רב אשי Rav Ashi הכי אמר
אמימר hachi amar Amemar here's what אמימר Amemar says הלכה כוותיה דשמואל
halacha k'vasi d'Shmuel
we rule like שמואל Shmuel that she needs a גט get at
least מספק. misafek. אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi so רב אשי
Rav Ashi says השתא דאמר אמימר הלכתא כוותיה דשמואל hashta d'amar Amemar
hilchasa k'vasi d'Shmuel now that we're ruling on שמואל Shmuel אם היה
יבמה כהן im hayah yevamah kohen
if her brother-in-law is a כהן kohen and now she went ahead
and she accepted קידושין kiddushin from this other man, so שמואל Shmuel
is going to say oh she accepted קידושין kiddushin from another man
she needs a גט. get. Once this other man gives her גט
get what's the story? The כהן kohen her brother-in-law is not going
to be able to do יבום, yibum, right, because she'll now be
a גרושה, grushah, everybody with me here? So that will obviate the
possibility of יבום, yibum, so if we're now going to demand a
גט, get, now this guy is in a is stuck. So the
point here is חולץ לה choritz lah he has to do חליצה
chalitzah and so what can he do? So what we're going to
say, rather than have the first the guy that married her do
a גט get and then he will not be able to do
יבום yibum and then he'll have to do חליצה, chalitzah, let's just
reverse the order, have her first do חליצה, chalitzah, חולץ לה ושרי
ליה choritz lah v'sharei lei and then let her stay with the
man she's currently married with, right? Rather than our normal approach would
be hey you married this guy you weren't supposed to marry her
you needed יבום yibum or חליצה, chalitzah, you know reverse what you
did get a גט get from him and now we'll do either
the יבום yibum or חליצה, chalitzah, but here the גמרא... Gemara... or
saying one minute if the guy is a כהן kohein I mean
the brother-in-law then you're only you're only going to wind up doing
חליצה chalitzah anyway so you might as well have him do the
חליצה chalitzah first and then let her stay married to the guy
she's married to. Okay? Yeah clear? That's what it says.
You could argue it's more radical because in this circumstance where the
brother-in-law is a כהן kohein and she married she did קידושין kiddushin
with some other guy that she could she should stay even without
the חליצה.
chalitzah. Well but שמואל Shmuel says she needs a גט get
since she's some
yeah or maybe right exactly so we're never going to get away
without the גט. get. So since it's got to be a חליצה
chalitzah anyway have him do the חליצה chalitzah first and let her
stay with the second guy.
So the גמרא Gemara says איתסרא ושריא לה. it'asra v'sharya la.
So that's what רב אשי Rav Ashi says. So the גמרא Gemara
challenges אי הכי אי הכי ee hachi ee hachi like is this
go like it's sort of like you know this is the opposite
makes sense. אם כן מצינו חוטא נשכר im kein matzinu choteh niskar
the sinner is rewarded. This guy married her when he shouldn't have
and now he's going to benefit that it's going to sort of
lead to him being allowed to stay married to this woman because
it forces the other guy the brother-in-law to do חליצה. chalitzah. Now
that's true anyway the brother-in-law's going to have to do חליצה chalitzah
but if we allow it to be done in this order he's
going to benefit from his wrong action. אלא אם היה ela im
haya so forget that. We won't allow that. Presumably we'll demand a
גט get and then the כהן kohein will do חליצה chalitzah and
then this woman will be out from both potential husbands. Okay. So
that we're not going to say. אלא ela what we are going
to say is אם היה יבמה ישראל im haya yevamah Yisrael if
her brother-in-law was a ישראל Yisrael then נותן לשני גט והותרה לו.
nosin l'sheni get v'hutra lo.
The second guy gives her a גט get and then she becomes
permissible to do יבום yibum with her brother-in-law. So meaning the חידוש
chidush then is what's the חידוש chidush fine get a גט get
from the man you did קידושין kiddushin reverse that and then be
permissible to do יבום yibum with your brother-in-law. What's the חידוש? chidush?
Well part of the חידוש chidush of all of this and that's
why there's a long תוספות Tosfos trying to figure out the הלכה
למעשה halacha l'maaseh is how much do we begin to compare this
case to the case about the woman who married a you know
this other guy when there was testimony that her husband was dead
and then the husband shows up and then she's אסורה assura to
both husbands right? Remember that? That big חידוש chidush of our first
משנה? Mishnah? So maybe we should say the same thing here. Maybe
we should say she married this guy meaning it's no testimony that
he's dead this is just a woman that סתם stam went ahead
and married a guy when she should have got יבום yibum or
חליצה. chalitzah. It could have maybe also been because there was a
misunderstanding whether the guy was alive or dead but it doesn't matter
right now she's somewhat is married to her first guy באה ואמרה
ba'ah v'omrah that's the משנה Mishnah but that's not this discussion. This
discussion is just where the קידושין kiddushin is תופס. tofes. Okay? So
she has a זיקה zika to the first guy the brother-in-law so
she's quasi-married to him and she's really married to the guy she
accepted קידושין kiddushin from according to שמואל Shmuel right? So it's like
the reverse. The second guy's the one she's really married to the
first guy's the one she's quasi-married to right? So there maybe we
should say in that case even though the kid maybe isn't a
ממזר mamzer because you know against רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva maybe we
should say she can
never she can't you know consummate it with either of them. תצא
מזה ומזה teitze mi-zeh u-mi-zeh type of a thing. So so the
גמרא Gemara is saying that not that way that actually she can
get a גט get from the first guy and go and go
I mean from the second guy and go and do יבום yibum
with the brother-in-law. The actual is accepted and the גמרא Gemara considered
the opposite that the that the what do you call it that
the brother-in-law could do חליצה chalitzah and she could stay with the
second guy. So the חידוש chidush here is that we're allowing it
to potentially to resolve itself and not say she has to extricate
herself from both of these men. Okay? And that is very different
than the tone we set earlier. Now תוספות Tosfos questions this. תוספות
Tosfos really isn't so sure this is true. And תוספות Tosfos says
that you know because of everything that went before this in the
גמרא. Gemara. So תוספות Tosfos says this might only be in a
case where all she had was קידושין kiddushin with the second guy.
Right you remember if she has in the case where her husband
is reported dead she only has קידושין kiddushin with the second man
and he turns up alive it doesn't have all the negative consequences.
She goes back to her husband. Right? So תוספות Tosfos says maybe
that's the same point here. She has קידושין kiddushin with this other
guy and therefore we allow her to say get divorced from guy
two go back to your go to the brother-in-law or maybe the
brother-in-law does חליצה chalitzah stay with guy two. Okay but that's because
it's only
קידושין kiddushin but if נישואין nisuin maybe if they had consummated maybe
we would lump on all of those negative consequences that we're familiar
with from the beginning of the פרק. perek. So that's not clear
in the גמרא. Gemara. That's an issue that תוספות Tosfos brings up.
Charlie you had a question from before.
And this entire discussion would seem to be only according to the
opinion יש זיקה? yesh zika?
Yeah if you said that the קידושין kiddushin isn't תופס. tofes. Yeah
it would logically be really consistent with the יש זיקה yesh zika
idea. Again the גמרא Gemara doesn't explicitly connect it but yes that's
clearly what it's connected to.
Isn't it bothersome that we have a different ruling whether her יבם
yavam is a כהן kohein or ישראל? Yisrael?
Well in the end it's not a different ruling. In the end
what we're saying is that the guy she married has to divorce
her and then you take it from there. So the guy she
married divorced her. If her brother-in-law is a כהן kohein he's stuck
she's a גרושה gerusha has to do חליצה. chalitzah. If her brother-in-law
is a ישראל Yisrael he can go ahead and do יבום. yibum.
Even the first scenario where she does חליצה chalitzah first he still...
No that's the גמרא's Gemara response. The point is we don't do
חליצה chalitzah first. We first
benefit because he jumped in and did קידושין kiddushin when he shouldn't
have done it and he forced the guy's hand to do חליצה?
chalitza? So therefore we're not going to let him benefit as a
consequence. We're going to say גט get and then גט get and
then the brother-in-law's left with, okay, I can't do יבום yibum with
this גרושה, gerusha, so he has to do חליצה. chalitza. But in
both cases the הלכה halacha winds up the same, that first you
give a גט get from the second guy and then the brother-in-law
makes the appropriate decision. Now תוספות Tosafot has an interesting question which
is, what if the brother-in-law was anyway planning on doing חליצה? chalitza?
It's one thing that the second guy shouldn't be able to force
the brother-in-law's hand, right, and ah, I'm going to force you to
do חליצה chalitza and I'm going to stay married to her, otherwise
you would have done יבום, yibum, I would have been out of
the picture, ha, I'll marry her first, you'll be forced to do
חליצה chalitza and so on. Okay, but what if the brother-in-law was
anyway wanted to do חליצה? chalitza? Would he be allowed to do
חליצה chalitza and the second guy allowed to stay married to her?
So תוספות Tosafot says in that case yes, actually he would be
allowed. We're not going to force him to, you know, we're not
going to say it's אסור assur for you to do חליצה chalitza
first, we're just going to say we're not going to, you know,
have this scenario make you do opposite, you know, force you to
do חליצה chalitza if you would have wanted to do יבום, yibum,
you know, and let this guy win out.
Okay? Was that even with קידושין kiddushin or
was that even with נישואין? nisuim? No, no, no, according to תוספות
Tosafot only by קידושין. kiddushin. So by the way they would force
him? Yeah, well by תוספות Tosafot not just force him, there would
be all the negative consequences. So anyway, that's what תוספות Tosafot says.
So if you look at the
תוספות, Tosafot, נותן לשני גט nosein lashaini get towards the end he
says, actually he says, let me see if I can find the
key line, he says like this.
So נותן לשני גט nosein lashaini get if you look three lines
down into it, the line that ends with ומותרת umutteres towards like
the last third of that line, he says like this: וכן היה
רבינו תם הלכה למעשה. V'chein haya Rabbeinu Tam halacha l'maaseh. You see
that? And that goes through a real case: הלכה למעשה באשה שלא
ידעה שהיה לה יבם. Halacha l'maaseh b'isha shelo yada'ah shehaya lah yavam.
She didn't know she had a brother-in-law. ונתקדשה, V'nitkadsha, and she got
married. והתירה למקדש אחר חליצת היבם. V'hitirah l'mikadesh achar chalitzat hayavam. And
he said okay, so the brother-in-law can do חליצה chalitza and you
can stay married to the guy you took קידושין kiddushin from because
that was a case where the guy anyway would have done חליצה.
chalitza. So if the guy was anyway planning on doing חליצה, chalitza,
we let him do חליצה chalitza first to let her stay with
the guy she
was married to.
That was the case. I don't know, was it the case? In
any case if you go to the three lines before, you want
to go to the beginning, אומר רבינו תם, Omer Rabbeinu Tam, beginning
of תוספות Tosafot דאיירי. d'ayiri.
Anyway, fine. Okay. Oh, actually תוספות Tosafot here emphasizes that it was
only קידושין kiddushin and not נישואין. nisuim. Okay, the issue about whether
they would have done חליצה chalitza first or not, I forget which
תוספות Tosafot that was in, anyway one of these תוספות Tosafot also
makes that point. Okay, so A says it was קידושין kiddushin not
נישואין nisuim and B the only reason we allow the guy to
do חליצה chalitza first and let her stay with the second guy
is if that's what the guy would have done anyway. We just
don't let the second guy benefit from having forced the hand of
the first guy.
Okay so yeah, I mean they didn't do קידושין kiddushin and נישואין
nisuim together the way we do, but like you could have a
scenario they had קידושין, kiddushin, then run to the חופה, chupah, the
כהן kohein runs...
in theory yeah.
Is the כתובה ketubah written at קידושין? kiddushin?
Is the כתובה ketubah written at קי— No, in general it would
have been written at נישואין. nisuim.
Okay, because I was trying to compare these two cases like you
were saying before about the first series of punishments, and yesterday we
were saying we might not see them as punishments but just because
of the result of the conditions that were... Right, so here she's
not really being looked at in the same way, she's not being
punished...
Exactly, exactly. Okay, the second point about what he wanted to do,
it's the
גמרא Gemara says like this: והדר קאמר, V'hadar ka'amar, if you look
like, I don't know, the line under רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, he
says: והדר קאמר הכא יתקרי אידכר, v'hadar ka'amar hacha yitkrei idkar, הני
מילי דקאמר חולץ ליבם ושריא לבעלה, hani mili d'ka'amar choletz l'yavam v'sharya
l'ba'alah, דמשמע חולץ בעל כרחו, d'mashma choletz b'al korcho, that you're forcing
his hand to do חליצה, chalitza, שכופין אותו אף על פי שברצונו
היה מייבם. shekofin oto af al pi shebirtzono haya meyabem.
That, we therefore we don't let him benefit because you forced his
hand to do חליצה chalitza אילו קידש. ilu kidesh. משום הכי פרק
יתקרי אידכר. Mishum hachi parek yitkrei idkar. אבל אם מדעתו היה חולץ,
Aval im mida'ato haya choletz,
if he anyway wanted to do חליצה, chalitza, היתה מותרת לו, hayeta
muteres lo,
then you let him do חליצה chalitza first so the second guy
can stay married. And according to תוספות Tosafot only if it was
קידושין, kiddushin, not נישואין. nisuim Okay, but רש״י Rashi sounds like even
in a נישואין nisuim, case. So that's another big question. Would we
allow, would we, you know, if it actually went through with נישואין,
nisuim. would it have all those negative consequences we're familiar with? Let's
get back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, so אמר רב גידל אמר רב, Amar Rav Gidel Amar Rav,
so said רב גידל Rav Gidel in the name of רב. Rav.
אמר רב חייא בר יוסף אמר רב, Amar Rav Chiya bar Yosef
Amar Rav, said now in the name of רב, Rav, יבמה קידושין
אין בה, Yevama kiddushin ein bah, a sister-in-law who needs חליצה, chalitza,
קידושין kiddushin won't take effect, but נישואין יש בה, nisuim yesh bah,
there is נישואין. Now what does that mean? Says the גמרא: Gemara:
אי קידושין אין בה נישואין נמי אין בה. Ei kiddushin ein bah
nisuim nami ein bah. So said רב גידל Rav Giddel in the
name of רב. Rav. So said רב גידל Rav Giddel in the
name of רב, Rav, אמר ליה חייא amar lei Chiyah excuse me
בר יוסף bar Yosef אמר רב, amar Rav, said that now in
the name of רב, Rav, יבמה Yevama קידושין kiddushin אין בה, ein
bah, a sister-in-law who needs חליצה, chalitza, קידושין kiddushin won't take effect,
but נשואין יש בה, nisuin yesh bah there is נשואין. nisuin Now
what does that mean? Says the גמרא, Gemara, אי קידושין אין בה
נשואין נמי אין בה, ee kiddushin ein bah nisuin nami ein bah,
if קידושין kiddushin didn't take effect, נשואין nisuin. didn't take effect. Okay,
so אימא קידושין ונשואין אין בה. ema kiddushin ve'nisuin ein bah. Alright
fine, they both don't take effect. אי בעית אימא, Ee ba'is teima,
מאי נשואין. mai nisuin. Of course that's like a silly statement just
to say if there's no קידושין, kiddushin, so תוספות Tosafos says what
it might mean that נשואין אין בה nisuin ein bah because נשואין
nisuin of course means if they slept together, right? So נשואין אין
בה nisuin ein bah might be a way of saying she doesn't
exactly what we've been dealing with, that she doesn't suffer all the
negative consequences after נשואין, nisuin right? So by saying נשואין אין בה
nisuin ein bah means even if they go through with נשואין, nisuin,
we're not going to necessarily say now תצא מזה ומזה והולד ממזר
tetzei mizeh umizeh vehavlad mamzer etc. all those negative things. So actually
it might be very important statement to say נשואין אין בה. nisuin
ein bah. ואי בעית אימא, Ve'ee ba'is teima, and if you want
I could say מאי נשואין יש בה, mai nisuin yesh bah, what
does it mean that there is נשואין? nisuin, בזנות, Biznus, if
it means that the act of sex has consequences to the with
the second guy, to רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna like רב המנונא, Rav
Hamnuna, דאמר רב המנונא, de'amar Rav Hamnuna, שומרת יבם שזינתה, shomeret yavam
she'zinta, a woman that was required יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza and
she went ahead and she had sex with another man, אסורה ליבמה,
asura le'yevama, she's forbidden to her brother-in-law, okay, so the act of
sex makes her forbidden sort of like a quasi type of an
adultery. So נשואין יש בה nisuin yesh bah doesn't mean as a
good thing, it means that there's significance to the fact that he
actually consummated with a second guy. Now does that mean that we
keep on her all of the negative consequences like we saw in
the first משנה? mishna? Not clear, but at least she's now אסורה
asura to the brother-in-law and and now יבום yibum is out of
the question.
No, no, they're just an איסור לאו issur lav or whatever, but
anyway it would not, no she would still need חליצה. chalitza. Okay,
ואי בעית אימא ve'ee ba'is teima and if you want you could
say לעולם תימא מעיקרא, le'olam teima me'ikara, קידושין אין בה נשואין יש
בה, kiddushin ein bah nisuin yesh bah, there is נשואין, nisuin? which
means what? Which means she requires a גט. get. Why should she
require a גט? get? דמחלפה באשה שהלך בעלה למדינת הים. demichlefa be'isha
she'halach ba'alah limedinat hayam. This is like a woman whose husband went
למדינת הים, limedinat hayam, then the husband shows up, so she technically
married to the second guy? No, but she requires a גט get
because it looks like she's married to the second guy. So here
too she follows through with נשואין, nisuin, right? So she here might
be she's not technically married to the guy because she's a שומרת
יבם, shomeret yavam, but nevertheless it looks like it, right? If a
woman has a real husband alive in front of us and then
she starts looking living with another guy, it doesn't look like she's
married to him, it looks like adultery, she shacked up with this
other guy who isn't her husband. But if her husband is במדינת
הים bemedinat hayam and there's a report that he's dead, it looks
like she's married to the second guy. Or if she doesn't have
a husband, she only has a brother-in-law and she's only waiting יבום
yibum or חליצה, chalitza, how many people would know that it's not
חל chal if he accepts קידושין kiddushin from another guy? It actually
looks like she is married to the second guy. So in those
cases even though technically she's not, because it looks like she is,
נשואין יש בה nisuin yesh bah she needs a גט, get, okay.
And again that gets to the idea that some of the consequences
in our first משנה, mishna, that she's taken, you know, that she
requires a גט get and all those negative things, might have to
do with the reality not so much of a קנס, knas, but
the reality that it's like she's married to the second guy as
well, okay, and therefore you have to deal with all those realities.
Okay, so we have three explanations. נשואין אין בה Nisuin ein bah
which might mean the exact opposite of what נשואין יש בה nisuin
yesh bah means, which is there's no negative consequence, just go back
and do יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza with the guy. Or נשואין
יש בה nisuin yesh bah, in the fact that you're אסורה asura
to the brother-in-law. Or the real powerful נשואין nisuin, יש בה, yesh
bah, I mean not necessarily good but powerful, in that it really
is seen of, even though technically there's no קידוש kiddush there's no
marriage, once you actually start living together, and since the relationship to
the brother-in-law is not real קידושין kiddushin it's only a זיקה zika
or whatever, it looks enough like a real marriage that we're going
to have to deal with the consequences and we're going to have
to say you have to give a גט get and possibly a
lot of other things. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבי ינאי, Amar Rabbi
Yannai, בחבורה נמנו וגמרו, bichabura nimnu ve'gamru, in the sort of college
they got together, you know, the rabbinic college they got together, they
voted,
אין קידושין תופסין ביבמה. ein kiddushin tofsin biyevama. Against שמואל Shmuel that
there is no קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, now whether rabbinically you need a
גט get after נשואין, nisuin, that I we don't know, that we
we're leaving as an open question. But the קידושין kiddushin does not
take effect. Okay, by the way you know it's so amazing, right,
we thought we were done with יבמות, yevamos, right? We thought we
were in I mean not מסכת יבמות Masechet Yevamot but the concepts
of יבום. yibum. And here we get such a critical idea about
this that שמואל Shmuel had about זיקה, zika, that the relationship to
the first husband is powerful enough or that transfers to the brother-in-law
that it prevents קידושין kiddushin from being חל chal with another guy.
Exactly, it would have been nice to have heard about this earlier.
Okay anyway, אין קידושין תופסין ביבמה. ein kiddushin tofsin biyevama. אמר ליה
רבי יוחנן Amar lei Rabbi Yochanan so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said,
רבי, Rabbi, לא משנתנו היא זו, lo mishnatenu hi zu, one minute,
what's the big חידוש? chiddush? I can show you that this is
a משנה. mishna. Not our משנה mishna but a different משנה. mishna.
What משנה? mishna? היא זו, Hi zu, דתנן ditnan we learned in
a משנה: mishna: האומר לאשה הרי את מקודשת לי לאחר שאתגייר, Ha'omer
le'isha harei at mekudeshet li le'achar she'etgayer,
you are betrothed to me after I convert. This is a non-Jew
saying this to her. או לאחר שתתגיירי, O le'achar she'titgayeri, he says
it to a non-Jewish woman. Gives her the ring and says הרי
את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li after you're after you convert.
ולאחר שאשתחרר Ve'achar she'ishtachrer after I get freed, he's a slave, ולאחר
שתשתחררי ve'achar she'tishtachreri after you're free. ולאחר שימות בעליך Ve'achar she'yamut ba'alech
after your husband dies. ולאחר ש... Ve'achar she... ואחר שתמות אחותייך, Ve'achar
shetamut achotayich, after your sister, my wife dies, right? 'Cause you can't
marry her while, you know, it's a, you know, marrying a wife's
sister while the wife is alive. או לאחר שיחלוץ יבמייך, O le'achar
sheyachalotz yevamayich, יבמייך, yevamayich, יבמייך, yevamayich, יבמייך, yevamayich, יבמייך. yevamayich.
Anyway,
after your brother-in-law does חליצה, chalitza, אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshet. And in
all those cases, she's not married. Why is she not married? Because
he's trying to do something that he can't be done right now.
The גמרא Gemara is going to compare it to מקנה אדם דבר
שלא בא לעולם. makne adam davar shelo ba la'olam. Okay? So it's
not possible right now, therefore the act is meaningless. Okay? The question
is, why does, I don't know, why does, why is it not,
all these cases if one of them is not Jewish or a
slave or the sister's alive, you know, you understand why it's not
חל. chal. Why is it not חל chal when there's a brother-in-law
who hasn't done חליצה? chalitza? Right? That's just an איסור לאו. issur
lav. Okay? So he says, ah, ah look, it's a משנה. Mishnah.
You see that if you try to do קידושין kiddushin into a
woman awaiting חליצה, chalitza, it doesn't take effect. It's a pretty clear
proof. So, אמר ליה, amar lei, so that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said back to רבי ינאי. Rabbi Yannai. So רבי ינאי Rabbi
Yannai said back to him, אי לאו דדלית ליה חספא, ei lav
dedalyat li chaspa, מי משכחת מרגניתא תותיה? mi mashkachat marganita tuteih? Had
I not removed the piece of pottery, you never would have found
the jewel hiding underneath it. You know, sometimes you say something and
then once you say it, oh it's so obvious, look you see
it everywhere, right? That's like we were talking about about the whole
idea of the other way of interpreting this משנה, Mishnah, what these
negative consequences are. Once you say it, it's so obvious. Sure, it's
obvious now that I've, now that I've sort of shown you the
light. But before I showed you the light, you wouldn't have realized
that. Now why wouldn't you have realized that? I mean come on,
that's what the משנה Mishnah says, that קידושין kiddushin doesn't work with
a woman awaiting חליצה. chalitza. No, you would have, so let's take
a look. So okay, maybe it is obvious but you wouldn't have
paid attention to it. So אמר ליה ריש לקיש, amar lei Reish
Lakish, so now ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, אי לאו דדקלסך ei
lav dadekalshach
גברא רבה. gavra raba. He said to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, if
this, if this great man had not praised you (not exactly clear
where he was praising him, but basically he acknowledged that this was,
maybe said that you found a pearl). Anyway, if he had not
praised you, הוה אמינא לך אנא, hava amina lach ana, I would
have said you can't prove anything from that משנה. Mishnah. Why can't
you prove anything from that משנה? Mishnah? מתניתין רבי עקיבא היא, matnitin
Rabbi Akiva hi, דאמר אין קידושין תופסין בחייבי לאוין. de'amar ein kiddushin
topsin bechayavei lavin. That's,
yes, that משנה Mishnah says that it doesn't work with a sister-in-law,
to be מקדש mekadesh a woman awaiting חליצה. chalitza. But that doesn't
prove that that's, that that's the consensus. Maybe that's just a רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position that says it doesn't work with a woman
who there's a prohibition of a לאו. lav. It doesn't tell you
it's a, it's a consensus position because it's a case of a
שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. Okay? So you wouldn't have been able to
prove it. Alright? Which might be, anyway what רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai
meant. רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai meant like, okay now you understand that
that's what's going on in that משנה. Mishnah. Okay, maybe you would
have otherwise would have read that משנה Mishnah otherwise. And ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish says, yeah you could have read the משנה Mishnah otherwise
to tell you that it was a, that it was a רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position, not a consensus position. So, אין קידושין—so ein
kiddushin the גמרא Gemara says one minute, we could not have said
that משנה Mishnah about קידושין kiddushin was רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
that's why it did not work with the sister-in-law, I mean with
whatever, the woman awaiting
חליצה. chalitza. ואי רבי עקיבא, ve'ei Rabbi Akiva, כי אמר לה לאחר
שיחלוץ יבמיך, ki amar lah le'achar sheyachalotz yevamayich, ליפשו בה קידושין. lifshu
bah kiddushin. קידושין Kiddushin actually should work. That can't be רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. Because according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, קידושין kiddushin would
work in this case. Why would it work? דהא שמענא ליה לרבי
עקיבא, deha sham'ina leih leRabbi Akiva, we know רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
is of the position דאמר אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם. de'amar
adam makne davar shelo ba la'olam. You can, you can transfer ownership
of something that does not yet exist. And now the גמרא Gemara
is going to do for the next דף daf is sort of
put into one big category anything that is similar to this idea
of transferring ownership of something that does not exist. Obviously these cases
are different. Okay? And let's take a look, as we go through
the cases, it'll be obvious what some of these differences are. דתנן,
detnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, דף צג עמוד א. daf
tzadik gimmel amud aleph. קונם שאני עושה לפיך. Konam she'ani osa leficha.
A woman says to her husband, right, a woman's earnings goes to
her husband. She says to her husband קונם, Konam, which is a
way of making אסור בנדר assur beneder like a קרבן, korban, what
the labor that I produce should be אסור assur to your mouth.
You won't be able to eat or benefit from the labor that
I produce, even though the husband normally gets the wife's earnings. So
לוקח loke'ach אין צריך להפר, ein tzarich lehafer, he does not have
to annul it because she doesn't have rights to it. The husband
is entitled to it. You can't annul some—you can't make אסור בנדר
assur beneder something that isn't yours.
רבי עקיבא אומר, יפר, Rabbi Akiva omer yafer he has to annul
it שמא תעדיף עליו יותר מן הראוי לו. shema ta'adif alav yoter
min hara'uy lo.
When you say שאני עושה לפיך, she'ani osa leficha, meaning "I won't
do anything for you"? Or "whatever I produce you can't have"?
No, the what I do you can't have. What I produce should
be a קרבן, korban, should be אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah to your
mouth.
Expect him not going to do anything for you.
No,
but whatever the labor I produce is אסור assur to you. Okay?
So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you have to be מיפר. meifer.
שמא תעדיף עליו יותר מן הראוי לו, Shema ta'adif alav yoter min
hara'uy lo, because she might actually produce more than the husband is
entitled. There's a whole question about, you know, she gets, she gets
food, he pays for the food bills in exchange for her earnings.
What if her earnings exceed the amount that he's paying for the
food bills? What if... exceed significantly that amount or it's an extra
earnings that normally she wouldn't have done? So we'll worry about all
that in כתובות. Kesubos. But Rabbi Akiva says there are some times
that she will actually produce something that he won't be entitled to
and therefore that and in those cases the נדר neder will take
effect and if he doesn't want it to take effect in those
cases because he actually it is her property he would have to
annul it. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute the גמרא Gemara
says okay very nice that it will be her fruit but right
now it doesn't exist. So how can she make right a נדר
neder is different than a שבועה, shvua, a שבועה shvua is an
oath I will do this. A נדר neder is changing the status
of the object. How can she make the status of the object
forbidden you know what she produces if what she has produced doesn't
exist yet? So how does Rabbi Akiva say that it works? So
what do you see? You see that Rabbi Akiva says that you
can you can make אסור assur by נדר neder something that doesn't
exist in the world. So the גמרא Gemara is going to put
this into a generic category of אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם
Adam makne davar shelo ba l'olam you can do transactions with things
that don't yet exist. So if that's true he would also say
you could do קידושין kiddushin with a with a woman that hasn't
had חליצה. chalitza. So clearly therefore our משנה Mishna that says you
can't do קידושין kiddushin is not Rabbi Akiva and again it proves
that everybody agrees you cannot do קידושין kiddushin with that woman because
that woman that case is not a Rabbi Akiva case. Rabbi Akiva
actually would say that those types of transactions do work.
Okay. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma really should have said לא
אמרה כלום. lo amra klum.
What no because תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and Rabbi Akiva aren't debating
that point they're only maybe they both agree אדם מקנה דבר שלא
בא לעולם. Adam makne davar shelo ba l'olam. So the גמרא Gemara
says הא אתמר עלה ha itmar alah so no that you maybe
it's not a case that it doesn't yet exist it was said
to explain this אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע amar Rav Huna
brei d'Rav Yehoshua באומרת b'omeress יקדשו ידי לעושיהן yikdeshu yadai l'oseihen
she doesn't say the labor I produce will be אסור assur and
that labor doesn't exist yet she says my hands will be sanctified
to the one who creates them to God so I'm sanctifying my
hands meaning I'm making my hands אסור בנדר asur b'neder in terms
of not not for all usage but that which emerges from my
hands you know the labor that comes out of my hands that
is going to be for my it's very אסור. assur So the
same way you can like sanctify a tree for its fruit I
can sanctify my hands for the labor they produce וידים איתנהו בעולם
v'yadayim isnhu ba'olam the hands do exist. So therefore it's not sanctifying
something that doesn't exist it's sanctifying the hands for what they produce
and the hands do exist. Yeah Chali you had a question.
That would make what she produces אסור assur. to everyone including herself.
Yeah so it would יקדשו yikdeshu doesn't it mean straight הקדש? hekdesh?
There's a whole comparison of הקדש hekdesh and נדר neder that נדר
neder draws on the world of הקדש hekdesh but it's not exactly
it's can be more personalized so it means it's הקדש hekdesh towards
the husband you know but not הקדש hekdesh towards everybody. Yes.
But didn't you say everybody agrees קידושין kiddushin did not
take effect outside of
we're trying to prove that. We're trying to prove that. So we've
got a משנה Mishna that says that you can't marry a woman
before she gets חליצה chalitza so doesn't it prove that קידושין kiddushin
doesn't take effect everybody agrees. Ah maybe that's only a Rabbi Akiva
position because it's איסור לאו issur lav and Rabbi Akiva says and
then we're saying no
not Rabbi Akiva.
Oh I see. Right the thing it can't be Rabbi Akiva because
according to Rabbi Akiva קידושין kiddushin would have worked okay because you
know when she gets חליצה. chalitza. It doesn't work now. Right it
would work when she would get חליצה chalitza then it would take
effect. Yes.
Explain to me that the difference of relationship between the concept of
אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם Adam makne davar shelo ba l'olam
and a kind of ברירה breira logic right? In other words I'm
I want to establish a situation now that למפרע l'mafrea will take
effect.
What's
למפרע? l'mafrea? It's not למפרע l'mafrea the קידושין kiddushin can never take
effect now the איסור issur נדר neder can never take effect now
the thing never exists at this moment. It can only take effect
a year from now when the woman gets חליצה chalitza when she
converts or when the thing exists. ברירה breira is the that it's
taking effect now once some once some once some facts clarify themselves
you'll understand what it took effect on. But here the thing doesn't
right doesn't exist yet okay.
I mean the word retroactive that's what Dove just said.
It's not retroactive.
When we said when I say retroactive it can only be חליצה
chalitza now it could not be ייבום. yibum.
Right it would only work if חליצה chalitza would take effect. But
even when חליצה chalitza would take effect it would only work at
that time it wouldn't work retroactively.
But I understand but I'm just saying it's forcing a condition before
the condition exists.
Right it's not forcing it would it would be dependent on a
condition right. Same if it says after you convert you could decide
never to convert right. When that condition is met would it then
take effect at that time? Right. Yes clear? I mean right it
might not it might never take effect because that condition might never
be met. Nobody is forcing.
Yes but I understand but I'm just saying that here we're limiting
something.
We're not limiting. The brother might do ייבום yibum and then this
guy who's trying to marry her is out.
He could do ייבום? yibum? Sure.
Nobody is forcing him. Okay so anyway we've got this case that
these it doesn't work right even you know it won't work even
after conversion or or the sister dies or חליצה chalitza because he
did it at a time when it couldn't work. So that proves
that קידושין kiddushin doesn't work for a sister-in-law for a woman awaiting
חליצה. chalitza. because Rabbi Akiva would say such a kiddushin would work
later on when those situations change because אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא
לעולם. adam makneh davar shelo ba l’olam. And the Gemara is now
questioning whether Rabbi Akiva really does say אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא
לעולם. adam makneh davar shelo ba l’olam. Okay, by the way, you
do recognize the difference, right? In one case, first of all, it’s
a difference between נדר neder and קידושין. kiddushin. Another case is that
one is the question about the subjects of the matter, the man
and the woman that are doing קידושין kiddushin as opposed to the
object on which, you know, the act is being done. So even
if you try to say that הלכה halakhah sees the woman in
קידושין kiddushin as a type of an object, but it also applies
to a case where the man is saying after I convert, after
I get freed, you know. So there’s a lot of differences, but
the גמרא Gemara is just throwing them all in the same category.
Okay, and the ראשונים Rishonim point out the differences. Now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. ופליגא דרב נחמן בר יצחק. u-pliga d’Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak. This idea to say רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is a
case that you’re sanctifying the hands and that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
actually would not say אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם adam makneh
davar shelo ba l’olam argues with רב נחמן בר יצחק. Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak. דאמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, d’amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak,
רב הונא כרב, Rav Huna k’Rav, רב הונא Rav Huna follows רב,
Rav, ורב כרבי ינאי, v’Rav k’Rabbi Yannai, ורבי ינאי כרבי חייא, v’Rabbi
Yannai k’Rabbi Hiyya, ורבי חייא כרבי, v’Rabbi Hiyya k’Rebbe, ורבי כרבי מאיר,
v’Rebbe k’Rabbi Meir, ורבי מאיר כרבי אלעזר בן יעקב, v’Rabbi Meir k’Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov, ורבי אלעזר בן יעקב כרבי עקיבא. v’Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov k’Rabbi Akiva. All of these hold sort of follows the order
of the generations, going from the later generations to the earlier like
a רב תלמיד Rav talmid relationship. He wants to say that all
of these תנאים ואמוראים, Tannaim v’Amoraim, whatever, hold a similar position. Okay,
and he’s actually listing them in their order of their chronological and
רב תלמיד Rav talmid relationship to say that maybe in some way
this position was influenced רב Rav to תלמיד talmid and got passed
down. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman holds like רב—I’m Rav sorry—that רב
הונא Rav Huna holds like רב, Rav, ורב כרבי ינאי, v’Rav k’Rabbi
Yannai, ורבי ינאי כרבי חייא, v’Rabbi Yannai k’Rabbi Hiyya, ורבי חייא כרבי,
v’Rabbi Hiyya k’Rebbe, ורבי כרבי מאיר, v’Rebbe k’Rabbi Meir, ורבי מאיר כרבי
אלעזר בן יעקב, v’Rabbi Meir k’Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov, ורבי אלעזר בן
יעקב כרבי עקיבא. v’Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov k’Rabbi Akiva. All of these
hold the same position and it’s all going from a late generation
to an earlier one. דאמרו, d’amru, they all hold of the position
of
אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם adam makneh davar shelo ba l’olam
that you can do a transaction on something that does not yet
exist. And again, the transaction will take effect when the thing does
exist, when those necessary conditions are met, but you can do the
action now even though you don’t yet have all of the necessary
conditions. Okay, let’s take a look. And again, we’re going to see
that these are not really all the same category, but close enough.
Okay, so רב הונא מאי היא? Rav Huna mai hi? What’s רב
הונא? Rav Huna? דאתמר, d’itmar, המוכר פירות דקל לחברו. ha-mocher perot dekel
l’chavero.
You sell your friend the fruit of your palm tree before they
exist. Okay, so אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Huna, so רב הונא
Rav Huna says: עד שלא בא לעולם יכול לחזור בו. ad shelo
ba l’olam yachol lachzor bo.
So it doesn’t take effect until the fruit come into the world.
So until the fruit come into the world, you can retract your,
you know, you can go back on it. משבא לעולם, misheba l’olam,
once the fruit come into the world, אינו יכול לחזור בו, eino
yachol lachzor bo, you can’t retract. Then the transaction you did takes
effect once those fruit come into the world and therefore אדם מקנה
דבר שלא בא לעולם, adam makneh davar shelo ba l’olam, it doesn’t
take effect retroactively but it takes effect when the fruit come into
the world. ורב נחמן אמר, v’Rav Nachman amar, רב נחמן Rav Nachman
says, אף משבא לעולם יכול לחזור בו, af misheba l’olam yachol lachzor
bo,
even when they come into the world you can go back on
what you said because that transaction never took effect, never will take
effect.
It applies to the buyer?
Yeah, either side, exactly. Okay, so ואמר רב נחמן, v’amar Rav Nachman,
now parenthetically רב נחמן Rav Nachman says, מודינא, modina, I will concede
דאי שמיט ואכיל d’ee shemit v’achil that if the purchaser actually goes
ahead and grabs the fruit and eats it, לא מפקינן מיניה, lo
mafkinan mineh, we don’t make him pay, you know, we don’t make
him pay it back. Okay, meaning, so while we won’t enforce such
a transaction because it never really took effect, for some reason we
won’t also, you know, act to reverse it either if the guy
went ahead and acted on it. So what’s that about? What that
concession is about is not clear, but nevertheless, you know, is there
really some legal bindingness to it enough that allows him to seize
it, or is it just like a societal point—hey, since they all
agreed upon it, we’re going to sort of allow the status quo
to remain and we’re not going to and we’re not going to
disrupt the status quo if he went ahead and grabbed it? Anyway,
you do see though the position that certainly according to רב הונא,
Rav Huna, אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם, adam makneh davar shelo
ba l’olam, and it takes effect when that thing does come into
existence. Okay, so that’s רב הונא. Rav Huna. Then we say like
this. רב
דאמר, Rav d’amar, who’s רב? Rav? דאמר רב הונא אמר רב, d’amar
Rav Huna amar Rav, because very nicely, by the way, now it’s
רב הונא Rav Huna saying in the name of רב, Rav, so
there goes that chain of tradition. האומר לחברו, ha-omer l’chavero, שדה זו
שאני לוקח, sadeh zo she-ani lokeach, לכשאקחנה קנויה לך מעכשיו. lich-she-ekachenah knuyah
lach me-achshav. So here’s selling futures. רב Rav says if you say
to somebody: “This field that I am going to purchase, when I
purchase it, it’ll be—you should own it as of now.” Interestingly the
phrase “as of now.” I’ll say something about that in a minute.
קנה, kana, it works. When you go ahead and purchase that field,
then it automatically transfers to the guy you sold it to, even
though when you sold it you didn’t own it yet.
Okay, now, right,
the field, exactly, there’s a lot of differences, right? A, you’re talking
about the object or you’re talking about the, like, the people doing
the transaction, right? Like the case
about... Very often when the גמרא Gemara says כולהו סבירא להו, kulu
sevira lehu, everybody holds of the position, it doesn't mean literally the
same position. It means they're all holding of a related position. Okay,
but nobody is really claiming that one position necessarily forces you to
hold the other one, but they're all related positions. Now, two statements.
Number one is, there's a רמב"ם, Rambam, I think if I'm remembering
correctly, and some אחרונים Acharonim that say that even if we פוסקן
pasken אין אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם, ein adam makneh davar
shelo ba l'olam, if something, if you try to sell something that
you don't own, it exists but you don't own it, but it's
readily available, like, I basically sell you, I don't know what I'm,
you know, I'm going to the market later today, I'll buy you
a, I'll buy you a quart of milk, okay? Give me the
money and you'll own that quart, you know, and you'll own that
quart of milk as of now. I'm selling it to you now,
I'm going to buy it later. So some might say that does
work because that is not, yes, I don't own it, but there's
no question that I can easily get it under my control. It
exists, it's out there, everybody's selling quarts of milk. That type of
thing might be that I am able to sell it to you
as of now, even if you normally say אין אדם מקנה דבר
שלא בא לעולם. ein adam makneh davar shelo ba l'olam. It gets
into the whole world of futures, right? I mean, the whole stock
world of futures is essentially that. You can always buy it, the
stocks are readily available. Is that אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם
adam makneh davar shelo ba l'olam or not? That's one issue. The
מעכשיו me'achshav question is a different question, which is you don't, you
never wind up owning it retroactively, it doesn't seem. How can you
own something before the guy who sold it to you got it
in his possession? But the need to do the מעכשיו me'achshav has
to do with this long תוספות, Tosafot, long discussion, I won't get
into details, which is to what degree when the קנין kinyan takes
effect, when the object comes into the person's control, do you still
need some remnant of the מעשה קנין? maaseh kinyan? Okay? So for
example, if I pay you money for something, it's a field, then
when that field actually gets purchased, you still have the money that
I gave you in your possession. Even if you spent the money,
you would have to give me the money back if the purchase
didn't go through. So it's like you still have that money. Because
you still have that thing that did the קנין, kinyan, that act
that affected the קנין, kinyan, then it allows the קנין kinyan to
take effect when actually that would be when you get the field,
right? I gave you the money, you would still be holding the
money. When he got the field, because he still had that money
or owed me that money, it allowed it to take effect. But
let's say instead in a different, what happened was was that he
wrote me a שטר, shtar, and that שטר shtar got torn up,
okay? And then when you got the field, I don't have anything
that's left of the מעשה קנין maaseh kinyan when the field actually
comes in your possession. Maybe in that case, it doesn't transfer. Maybe
you need some remnant of the act of the קנין. kinyan. So
תוספות Tosafot says that's what מעכשיו me'achshav solves. מעכשיו me'achshav is saying
since we're somehow giving power to the act right now, even though
obviously I can't own the field at an earlier time than when
you got it in your control, but since you say מעכשיו, me'achshav,
it allows us that even if the שטר shtar gets burnt up
or gets destroyed, since we said מעכשיו, me'achshav, that act of קנין
kinyan that took place now was powerful enough to allow the transaction
to take effect once you did get in possession of the object.
Let me make sure I understand, clarify the facts. There are three
guys here, right? You're the owner of the field, I'm buying it
from you, and I'm saying to Michael when I buy it on,
say it's Monday, right? Right. So I'm gonna buy the field on
Friday from you, and then you will have ownership as of last
Monday.
Well no, so that's what תוספות Tosafot says. There's no way Michael
can own it as of last Monday if you didn't get it
till Friday. Right. So what the מעכשיו me'achshav does is it says
that because you said the word מעכשיו, me'achshav, the קנין kinyan that
you did on Monday, which is that you gave Michael the שטר,
shtar, that קנין kinyan will work even if come Friday the שטר
shtar has been destroyed. That's what תוספות Tosafot says the function of
the מעכשיו me'achshav is.
So then he will come into ownership as of Friday.
He comes in ownership as of Friday, but what מעכשיו me'achshav says
is that you don't need the קנין kinyan to continue through Friday.
The קנין kinyan can be done today. If you didn't say מעכשיו,
me'achshav, he would still have to be holding onto the שטר shtar
as of Friday.
I see, and so מעכשיו me'achshav is like a handshake in a
way.
Whatever it is, it's something that allows the whole קנין kinyan to
be meaningful today. But again, it only, the transfer only happens when
you get into possession of the object.
But is there such a position that says I don't get it
until Friday but still his ownership is as if it were?
Not that I know of, but who knows, yeah.
The reason
I can't get
the benefit, let's say it produced three days worth of fruit? Right.
I don't get that benefit.
Presumably, although again, maybe I'm not remembering something, but okay.
And if you didn't say מעכשיו me'achshav
and you gave me money,
then it would still work because you still haven't
spent the money.
Yeah, that's what תוספות Tosafot says. Okay, because you would still owe
him the money if it didn't go through.
Referred to it.
So when does an oral agreement take effect over, say there's no
written...
No oral agreement is binding, well, not no, but whatever.
It was an oral thing?
No, no, no. So that's what I'm saying. Right, but it wasn't
oral at the time, there was a transfer of a שטר. shtar.
No, he's saying it's torn.
Right, but it was on record and they said, well... Okay, but
let's say there were witnesses that testified that there was a שטר,
shtar, whatever, but you still need an act of some type of
an act, the act of giving. money, the act of writing a
document. It's not just proof, it's the, it's the instrument that effects
the transaction. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so
that's רב. Rav. רבי ינאי כרבי חייא, Rabbi Yannai ke-Rabbi Chiya, רבי
ינאי Rabbi Yannai holds like רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, ד-רבי ינאי הוה
ליה אריסא, de-Rabbi Yannai hava lei arisa, so, you know,
רב Rav holds like רבי ינאי. Rabbi Yannai. Who's רבי ינאי? Rabbi
Yannai? Because רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai had a sharecropper, דהוה מייתי ליה
כנתא דפירי כל מעלי שבתא. de-hava maytei lei kinta de-peirei kol ma'alei
shabta. He would bring him like a basket of fruit every מעלי
שבתא. ma'alei shabta. ההוא יומא נגה ליה, Hahu yoma naga lei, on
a certain מעלי שבתא ma'alei shabta it was getting dark, ולא אתא,
ve-lo ata, and he didn't come. So, and this, and רבי ינאי
Rabbi Yannai wanted to be able to eat the fruit on שבת,
Shabbos, but of course when he would get the fruit it wouldn't
have תרומות ומעשרות Trumos u-Ma'asros taken from it. You gotta do that
before שבת. Shabbos. So what did he do? שקל עשר מפירי דביתיה
עלייהו, Shakal asar mi-peirei de-veiteih aleiyhu, he took מעשר Ma'aser from fruit
he had in his own house עלייהו, aleiyhu, on the fruit that
would be coming to him on שבת Shabbos although the fruit was
going to get delivered on שבת Shabbos but it wasn't yet in
his possession. Okay, so again, it's not מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם,
makneh davar she-lo ba la-olam, it's taking מעשר Ma'aser on something שלא
בא לעולם. she-lo ba la-olam. Okay, also, if it's stuff that his
sharecropper produced, there's a whole question, presumably it's his, right? So is
it just that it's not in his רשות, reshus, it's not in
his, although he owns it it's not in his רשות? reshus? Or
תוספות Tosafos tries to say, well, maybe it wasn't technically his, maybe
their arrangement was such that it wasn't his until he delivered it.
Okay, but again, it's not exactly clear why this is the case.
I understand, I understand. So anyway, A, it's מעשר, Ma'aser, B, it
might have been רבי ינאי's Rabbi Yannai anyway, just not in his
control. Anyway, so again, these cases are not exactly the same. אתא
לקמיה דרבי חייא, Ata lekamei de-Rabbi Chiya, anyway, but nevertheless it works.
אתא לקמיה דרבי חייא, Ata lekamei de-Rabbi Chiya, he came to רבי
חייא. Rabbi Chiya. אמר ליה, Amar lei, and because he was felt
uncertain about whether what he did worked. So רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
said to him, שפיר עבדת, shapir abadt, you did well. דתניא, De-tanya,
למען תלמד ליראה את ה' אלקיך כל הימים, lema'an tilmad leyira es
Hashem Elokecha kol ha-yamim, in order that you should fear all days.
All days is אלו שבתות וימים טובים. elu Shabbosos ve-yamim tovim. So,
okay, even on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. So למאי
הלכתא, lemai hilchasa, what does
it come to tell you on שבת?
Shabbos? What? Well, okay, so what does it come to tell, now
this is a פסוק pasuk about מעשר, Ma'aser, okay, this פסוק, pasuk,
it's in the, it's in the context of מעשר. Ma'aser. So even
on, even on שבת Shabbos you take מעשר. Ma'aser. So is, is
it presumably what he's saying. So למאי הלכתא, lemai hilchasa, for what
purpose? אילימא לעשורי ומיכל, eileima le'asorei u-meichal, to tell you that you're
allowed to take מעשר Ma'aser on שבת? Shabbos? איצטרך קרא למישרא טלטול
דרבנן? itztrach kra lemishrei tiltul de-rabbanan?
Do you need the פסוק pasuk to allow something that's rabbinic? Now,
טלטול tiltul normally is used by מוקצה, muktzah, but the point here
is not מוקצה, muktzah, the point here is, is that the whole
prohibition of taking מעשר Ma'aser is only a rabbinic prohibition. So the
פסוק pasuk that's telling you מעשר, Ma'aser, you know, applies on שבת
Shabbos cannot be coming to tell you that you're allowed to take
מעשר Ma'aser on שבת. Shabbos. The פסוק pasuk wouldn't be needed to
מותר matir something that's
an איסור דרבנן. issur de-rabbanan. אלא, Ella, דף צ"ג עמוד ב', daf
tzadi gimmel amud beis, אלא לאו כי האי גוונא,
ella
lav
ki hai gavna, it must be coming for this case, that when
you took it because you didn't yet have it in your possession,
it still is going to work. Okay, now תוספות Tosafos also points
out that that's also a little strange because the only reason he
took it before it became in his possession was because he wasn't
rabbinically allowed to take it on שבת. Shabbos. So it's all still
because of a rabbinic issue. But anyway תוספות Tosafos also points out
that there's another problem which is you're supposed to take מעשר מן
המוקף. Ma'aser min ha-mukaf. Forget if you own it. It's also supposed
to be connected. All the food you take מעשר Ma'aser on is
all supposed to be physically in the same location, not some in
this warehouse and some in that one. So that's what he says.
It's coming to allow you in this type of a case when
you took it because of whatever your issues were going through, whatever
reason it was, whether it was rabbinic איסור issur of taking תרומות
ומעשרות Trumos u-Ma'asros on שבת, Shabbos, whatever the thing was that was
motivating you, at the end of the day you took it שלא
מן המוקף. she-lo min ha-mukaf. And nevertheless it's telling you that's okay
because you did it because you had to do it because it
was שבת, Shabbos, therefore that's okay and therefore don't worry about it.
What you did was fine. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said
back to him, והא קרו לי בחלמא, ve-ha karu lei be-chalma, but
one minute, it was read to me in a dream, קנה רצוץ,
kaneh ratzutz, the פסוק pasuk of a weak reed, a broken reed.
So מאי לאו הכי קאמרו לי, mai lav hachi ka-amru lei, this
must be what they're telling me from, you know, the message I
got from heaven must be telling me the following thing: הנה בטחת
לך על משענת הקנה הרצוץ הזה, hinei batachta lecha al mish'enes ha-kaneh
ha-ratzutz ha-zeh, behold you've put your faith, you've put your trust into
the, you know, into the support of this weak and broken reed.
So basically you're trying to rely on the idea, oh it was
okay to take it ערב שבת Erev Shabbos even though I didn't
yet have it in my possession, even though it wasn't מן המוקף,
min ha-mukaf, even though it wasn't all in the same place. Yeah,
you're relying on a very weak, you know, broken reed is what
you're supporting yourself on and seems to be I'm getting a message
I did the wrong thing. Presumably that's why he was anxious and
he came to ask his רבי Rebbi about the שאלה shaylah about
what, about what happened.
He did it anyway then afterwards he has this dream.
Afterwards he had this dream. So that's why he was feeling, that's
why he was feeling anxious and that's why he went and asked
and he, and he said, so no, so the רבי Rebbi said,
"No, you did fine. I have a פסוק." pasuk. Ah, but what
about this dream I had? So he says, "No, that's not what
the פסוק pasuk that they were referring to. הכי קאמרו לך, hachi
ka-amru lach, this is the פסוק pasuk that they, that it was
referring, that they were saying to you: קנה רצוץ לא ישבור, kaneh
ratzutz lo yishbor, a,
a broken reed or like a weak reed won't break, right? If
something is more flexible." Flexible as opposed to brittle, then it won't
break even if the winds come.
ופשתה כהה לא יכבנה upishtah khehah lo yikhbenah and like some type
of flax, you know, will not will not cause it to extinguish.
I don't know exactly the word.
Or extinguishing flickering flax.
Flickering flax? Okay, anyway, whatever. So the point is he quoted a
different פסוק pasuk that had קנה רצוץ kaneh ratzutz that actually was
telling you it was a good thing. Okay, pretty funny, broken reed,
but they meant to tell you it was a good thing that
you did.
All right, anyway, this like little tiny meditation on these two פסוקים
psukim and this metaphor of the broken reed. That's like a huge
implication for like a גישה gishah להלכה. lehalachah. In other words, in
what you can simultaneously say no, you need to be rigid or
you need to be flexible.
Right, exactly, because the whole idea is flexibility. That's true, absolutely.
Interesting piece here.
Absolutely. I love the idea, there's one תשובה, teshuvah, I forget what
the context was, but a certain ראשון Rishon had a שאילה shaylah
and in his response he said, you know, he said והנח
להם
לישראל וכו׳.
v'hanach lahem
l'Yisrael v'chulu. Okay, leave the Jewish people alone etc.
So then there's a
debate of the later אחרונים, acharonim, which line he was referring to.
Is he referring to the line הנח להם לישראל מוטב שיהיו שוגגים
ואל יהיו מזידים, hanach lahem l'Yisrael mutav sheyihyu shogegim v'al yihyu mezidim,
better they should be inadvertent transgressors rather than intentional transgressors, what they're
doing is wrong but let it be. Or was he saying הנח
להם לישראל אם אינם נביאים הם בני נביאים הם, hanach lahem l'Yisrael
im einam nevi'im hem b'nei nevi'im hem, that they're intuiting the right
thing and what they're doing is actually right. So it's just like
this קנה רצוץ kaneh ratzutz can go either way depending on how
you end the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, anyway, whatever the line. Okay, so
that is the idea that it works at least on מעשר ma'aser
not in your possession and it's being put in the same category.
רבי, Rebbi, now who's the רבי? Rebbi? דתניא d'tanya לא תסגיר עבד
אל אדוניו, lo tasgir eved el adonav,
do not hand over slave to his master, to his master. רבי
Rebbi אומר omer בלוקח עבד על מנת לשחרר הכתוב מדבר, beloke'ach eved
al mnat l'shachrer hakatuv medaber, that
if you take a slave and you purchase him from his other
master on the condition that you'll free him, you're not allowed to
not free him, which means not and presumably it's being read not
just that you're bound by your condition but that as a sort
of personal obligation or by the verse, but that actually your condition
takes effect and at the moment that you purchase him, the freedom
takes, you know, the manumission, the שחרור shichrur takes effect. So there
you see you freed him before you owned him and that act
of freeing him takes effect as soon as you purchase him. Okay,
היכי דמי? heichi dami? So what's the case? אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak דכתב ליה, d'chtav leh, because it's
not just you promised him, you actually did the act. You wrote
out a document that said, a document of manumission of שחרור, shichrur,
and it said לכשאקחך הרי עצמך קנוי לך מעכשיו, lich'she'ekachecha harei atzmecha
kanuy lach me'achshav, when I purchase you
then you now own yourself, again here's the as of now, whatever
as of now means in this context. Okay, so you wrote him
a document, a writ of שחרור shichrur of manumission, and that takes
effect when you actually go through with the purchase. So you see
the act took effect even though you did not yet own the
object to which the act is being done. רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
now that's רבי Rebbi so now רבי Rebbi follows like רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. Who's רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? דתנן d'tnan we learned in
the משנה Mishnah האומר לאשה ha'omer l'ishah
הרי את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li לאחר שאגייר, l'achar she'agayer,
you are married to me after I convert. לאחר שתתגיירי l'achar shetitgayeri
after you convert. לאחר שאשתחרר לאחר שתשתחררי l'achar she'eshtachrer l'achar shetishtachreri
after one of us gets free. לאחר שימות בעליך l'achar sheyamut ba'aleich
after your husband dies. לאחר שתמות אחותך l'achar shetamut achoteich after your
sister who I'm married to dies. לאחר שיחלוץ ליך יבמיך l'achar sheyachalotz
lach yevameich after your
brother-in-law does חליצה. chalitzah. אינה מקודשת, einah mekudeshet, does not work. That's
what we saw before, which was the proof that a woman who
is a שומרת יבם shomeret yavam you cannot have קידושין kiddushin with.
רבי מאיר אומר Rabbi Meir omer מקודשת, mekudeshet, it does work because
even though you don't have the condition satisfied right now, when those
conditions are satisfied it will take effect now. That's רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov, now that follows
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. דתניא d'tanya we learned
in the ברייתא braita יש
אומרים yesh omrim רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov אפילו
אמר פירות ערוגה זו תלושין יהיו תרומה על פירות ערוגה מחוברים, afilu
amar peirot arugah zu tlushin yihyu terumah al peirot arugah mechubarim, even
if somebody says that the fruit of this field or whatever, this
patch, row, right, that are picked will be תרומה terumah on the
fruit of the row that is still attached to the tree, and
you can't meaning when they get picked because you can't take תרומה
terumah while it's on the tree, but you say it will be
תרומה terumah on that, to take effect when those
get picked. או פירות ערוגה מחוברים על פירות זו תלושין, o peirot
arugah mechubarim al peirot zu tlushin, which is even a bigger חידוש.
chiddush. The fruit on the tree will be תרומה terumah on the
fruit that's already picked, but it'll take effect when the when I
actually pick those fruit. לכשיביאו שליש ויתלשו lich'sheyaviyu shalish v'yitlashu
when they get ripe enough and get picked. והביאו שליש ונתלשו v'heviyu
shalish v'nitlashu and they became ripe a third ripe and they were
picked, דבריו קיימים dvarav kayamim it takes effect. Okay, again so you
do an act that you don't yet have the necessary conditions for
the act to take effect, when those conditions are met the act
takes effect. Now again so It's not לא בא לעולם lo ba
l'olam or maybe they are if they're not ripe yet, whatever. But
whatever, let's say they are ripe but they haven't been picked, it's
not לא בא לעולם, lo ba l'olam, it's not even that you
don't own it. It's just that the conditions necessary for תרומה truma
to take effect are not not yet been met. But okay, these
are all similar enough positions. And finally רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, דתנן
ditnan what was said before, קונם שאני עושה לפיך אינו צריך להפר,
konam she'ani osa lefi hein oter lehafer, a woman makes אסור assur
בנדר b'neder what he's going to the work she'll produce, you don't
have to annul because it's not hers. רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva
omer, יפר yafer, he does and doesn't have to annul, שמא תרבה
יותר מן הראוי לה shema terbe yoter min haraui la because maybe
she'll produce more and therefore it will be owned by her and
therefore you have to annul it. Ah, but it doesn't exist yet!
Ah, but nevertheless you see that you can do something even though
it does not yet exist. Okay, so a whole list of ideas
under the broad umbrella of אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם. adam
makne davar shelo ba le'olam. What is this relevant to? Again, what
this is relevant to is that we had a משנה mishna that
said that a man can't marry a woman who was awaiting חליצה.
chalitza. So that proves that a woman awaiting חליצה chalitza שמא קידש
קידושין אינן תופסין בה shema kideish kidushin ain tofs bo is אינן
תופסין בה. ain tofs bo. So the גמרא Gemara says, well, maybe
it's רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, maybe it's not דברי הכל. divrei hakol.
But says it can't be רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva because רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva would say that that type of a קידושין kidushin would
work when she actually did get the חליצה. chalitza. So then that's
that question of, does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say אדם מקדיש דבר
adam makdish davar or מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם? makne davar shelo
ba le'olam? But again, the general upshot of the סוגיא sugya is
that a woman awaiting חליצה, chalitza, everybody agrees קידושין kidushin is not
תופסין, tofs im, presumably relating to the idea of יש זיקה. yesh
zika. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara gets back, so that was the
end of that סוגיא, sugya, now we get onto a new discussion.
בעי מיניה רב ששת Ba'ei minei Rav Sheshet asked רב ששת, Rav
Sheshet, עד אחד ביבמה מהו? ed echad b'yevama mahu? Let's say you
have one witness testifying not that the woman's husband died, but you
have one witness testifying about a brother-in-law. Now what does that mean?
So רש"י Rashi says initially we assume that
it means that he's testifying that the husband has died in order
to allow her to go through an act of יבום, yibum, not
to allow her to marry another guy, but allow her to do
an act of יבום. yibum. What would be the
story, מהו? mahu? טעמא דעד אחד ta'ama d'ed echad is the reason
we normally believe one witness, משום דמילתא דעבידא לאיגלויי לא משקר, mishum
d'milta d'avida l'igluye lo meshaker, since everything will eventually come to the
surface, be revealed, you know, because these facts have a way of
getting found out whether the husband's alive or not, so the עד
ed won't lie and
that's what backs up his statement generally that lets her marry another
guy. הכא נמי לא משקר. hacha nami lo meshaker. So here too
the עד ed won't lie, the witness won't lie because it'll all
eventually come to the surface. So therefore the same way she's allowed
to marry another guy, she should be allowed to do יבום yibum
with her brother-in-law. או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say טעמא
דעד אחד, ta'ama d'ed echad, no, the reason an עד אחד ed
echad is believed משום דהיא דייקא ומינסבא, mishum d'i dika u'minsva, because
she'll first investigate it before getting married? Okay, so even if you
need to back up the testimony of the עד אחד ed echad
with her investigation, why would that be different here? והכא כיון דזמנין
דרחמא ליה, v'hacha kivan d'zimnin d'rachma lei,
sometimes she loves the brother-in-law, לא דייקא ומינסבא, lo dika u'minsva, she
won't investigate so much. So meaning the גמרא Gemara is saying, first
of all, we should take a moment to pause and realize buried
in this discussion of do you believe an עד אחד ed echad
for her to marry the brother-in-law, the גמרא Gemara is finally saying
explicitly why we believe an עד אחד. ed echad. Do we believe
an עד אחד ed echad generally because all of the facts will
eventually come to the surface and therefore that alone is enough to
assume that we believe the עד אחד, ed echad, or do we
believe the עד אחד ed echad because it's backed up by the
assumption that she's going to do her own investigation? Okay, remember we
sort of raised that before, but here the גמרא Gemara is saying
it explicitly, these are two ways of understanding that. Because before a
lot of ראשונים Rishonim assumed that the whole reason for all the
fines was to force her to do an investigation, therefore תוספות Tosafot
says even when the גמרא Gemara says it's because it's עבידא לאיגלויי,
avida l'igluye, it'll come to the surface, we're it's still also plus
whatever investigation she's going to do, but it just doesn't mean primarily
it's based on her investigation. So it's interesting the way the ראשונים
Rishonim try to sort of smooth all of the edges. But nevertheless
the גמרא Gemara here is sort of seeing two possible reasons we
believe in עד אחד, ed echad, A, not related to the woman
in terms of the פשט p'shat of the גמרא, Gemara, it's just
because it'll all come to the surface, or B, because of the
investigation that the woman will do. And the question is what about
her marrying not a strange guy, but what about her marrying a
brother-in-law? Maybe she loves the brother-in-law and she won't investigate as much
as she has to. Well, maybe she marries, she loves this other
guy she wants to marry, not her husband, but somehow we assume
that she knows the brother-in-law, she's been around the brother-in-law more often,
you know, we're hopefully the גמרא's Gemara assuming it's not like she's
got her eye on some other man סתם ככה, stam kacha, but
a brother-in-law who's been around the house, maybe she's developed a relationship
with him and she actually is motivated to want to marry him
and therefore she's not going to investigate as much as she has
to. So what do we say? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
ליה רב ששת, amar lei Rav Sheshet, תניתוה, tanitu'a, we learned it.
אמרו לה, Amru la, if they said to her, back to our
משנה, Mishnah, מת בניך ואחר כך מת בעליך, mes baneich ve'achar kach
mes ba'alayich, your son died and then your husband died, ונתייבמה, u'nisyabma,
and then she did יבום yibum because her son had died first,
ואחר כך אמרו לה, ve'achar amru la, then they said חילוף הדברים,
chiluf hadevarim, it was the reverse, first the husband died and then
the son, and therefore you can't do יבום, yibum, תצא והולד ראשון
ואחרון ממזר, tetzei vehavlid rishon ve'acharon mamzer, she has to leave the
guy and the child's a ממזר mamzer and so on. Now he
wants to know why did the second, why was the second report
more authoritative than the first report? היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the
case? אי בתרי ותרי, iy betrei utrei, if the first report was
two witnesses and the second report was two witnesses, מאי חזית דסמכת
אהני סמוך אהני, mai chazis d'samchat ahanei, smoch ahanei, why do we
believe the second report more than the first? ועוד ממזר, ve'od mamzer,
what do you mean that the kid is a ממזר? mamzer? Because
now it's clear that she wasn't allowed, that it was an איסור
issur of with her brother-in-law and there wasn't a מצווה mitzvah of
יבום. yibum. ספק ממזר הוא, safek mamzer hu, he's a doubtful ממזר
mamzer because there's one report that says it was a מצווה mitzvah
of יבום, yibum, right? Okay, well whatever. וכי תימא לא דק, vechitayma
lo dak, maybe the משנה Mishnah isn't being precise, it really does
mean ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. דהא מני תני סיפא הראשון ממזר והאחרון
אין ממזר, dehaymi nitni seifa harishon mamzer ve'acharon ein mamzer, no because
in the end it's very precise about the ממזר mamzer issue. It
says the kid born before the second report is a ממזר, mamzer,
after the second report is not a ממזר mamzer in a different
case. שמע מינה דוקא קתני, shema mina davka katani, the משנה Mishnah
is being very precise. So why do we believe the second report
over the first? אלא לאו שמע מינה, ella lav shema mina, what
must be the case is חד, chad, that the first report was
only one witness and that one witness said you could go ahead
and do יבום yibum and she did יבום yibum and then that
was overridden by a later report of two witnesses that said that
they died in the reverse order and there's no מצווה mitzvah of
יבום. yibum. So that's the only way of explaining it.
וטעמא דאתו בי תרי אכחשוה, vetaima de'asu betrei akachshua, and therefore the
reason you believe the two is because it's two against one and
the two contradicted her. הא לאו הכי, ha lav hachi, but if
it had not been the two against one, נאמן, ne'eman, the testimony
of the one witness would have been sufficient for her to go
ahead and do יבום. yibum. So therefore you see you believe עד
אחד ed echad for her to do יבום. yibum. Okay, so do
you understand the case, meaning the משנה Mishnah basically had there was
a report that allowed her to do יבום yibum and then it
was overridden and it was said there was no מצווה mitzvah of
יבום. yibum. What made it overridden? It must have been that the
first report was only one witness. So you see then in a
general case you believe an עד אחד ed echad to say the
husband died to allow her to do יבום, yibum, and even though
she might already have a connection to the brother-in-law and she might
be a little incentivized not to research it so much because she's
eager to maybe do יבום yibum with the brother-in-law, that doesn't bother
us and we will say that we will still believe an עד
אחד ed echad in that case even though there's a possibility she
might not be as incentivized to go ahead and do a good
investigation. Okay, we will continue with this discussion tomorrow, which is very
important not just in terms of believing the עד אחד ed echad
for יבום, yibum, but it's important in terms of the whole question
of why do we at all believe the עד אחד ed echad
which has been the central question of this פרק. perek. Okay, we
will end here.